<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to the declaration of the imaginary Parliament of the unknowne Common-wealth of England, concerning the affaires past betwixt them of England, and the high and mighty lords the States Generall of the United Provinces: wherein their frivolous reasons are cleerly refuted; and their injust proceedings in the treaty of the aforesaid affaires, as in all their actions, manifestly discovered.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E678_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21805</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871509</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 104:E678[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to the declaration of the imaginary Parliament of the unknowne Common-wealth of England, concerning the affaires past betwixt them of England, and the high and mighty lords the States Generall of the United Provinces: wherein their frivolous reasons are cleerly refuted; and their injust proceedings in the treaty of the aforesaid affaires, as in all their actions, manifestly discovered.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by John Pieterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Rotterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to a Parliamentary declaration dated 7 Sept. 1652.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob. 10.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>United Provinces of the Netherlands. --  Staten Generaal.</term>
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE DECLARATION Of the Imaginary Parliament of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> concerning the Affaires paſt betwixt Them of <hi>England,</hi> and the High and Mighty Lords the States Generall of the United Provinces: <hi>Wherein their Frivolous Reaſons are cleerly refuted; and their injuſt proceedings in the Treaty of the aforeſaid Affaires, as in all their Actions, Manifeſtly diſcovered.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Pieterson</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>At Rotterdam, by <hi>John Pieterſon.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:123920:2"/>
            <p>THe Authors of this Declaration are the ſame men; who having acted that execrable parricide upon the King aſſumed the name of Parliament, which they had aboliſhed. Their beginning and growth hath beene formerly publiſhed, how a few lurking Sectaries being at firſt Members of Parliament, and conſorting in prodigious opinions in Religion and policy with the illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate rabble, became uſefull to the prime projectors, that under the maske of ſecuring Religion and Lawes, ſought to gaine the power of the State into their hands, being aſſiſted in their votes in the Lower Houſe, and applauded abroad for their proceedings by this buſy crew, who got into places in the Army, and at laſt gave law to their old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and having renounced faith and obedience to their King, with more eaſe ſcorned the bonds of aſſociation to their guides &amp; conſorts in the ſame impieties; And it cannot ſeem ſtrange to any that look on their Actions, to reade their ſhameleſſe Declarations, nor that they ſhould proceede with like injury to ſtrangers, as they have uſed to their King, Companions and Countreymen.</p>
            <p>They ſay, <hi>the returns which the people of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, made toward this Commonwealth will hardly be believed, if their ſufferings and deliverance, and the principles and spirit that acted in them then be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and the help they had from this Nation with the expence of Engliſh blood and treaſure.</hi> The people of theſe Provinces have with gratitude acknowledged the aſſiſtance they received from the Crown of England, and the affection and readines of the Engliſh Nation; And it were a juſt reproach if they ſhould make returnes for thoſe benefits to the Uſurpers of the regal power, deſtroyers of the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and Oppreſſors of this Nation. Can Nationall obligations be transferred to the Enemies of the Nation? And becauſe a Traiterous Army hath gotten power over the Nation, ſhall the Friends and Allies of the Nation aſſiſt the Uſurpers? This will hardly be believed, but eaſily that theſe Declarers have the impudence to pretend a right to all that which was due to the Crown that they have abjured.</p>
            <p>Though their boaſting of ſucceſſes be a principle part in all their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and ſo in this, <hi>Yet it is not intended</hi> (they ſay) <hi>to be very particular in mentioning the State of the affairs of this Commonwealth, as it ſtood when, oppreſſed by a Tyrant, they were neceſſitated to fly to Armes, for defence of their Lives and Eſtates, becauſe in Parliament they did but aſſert, and deſire the ſetling of their juſt and Native liberties.</hi> When over particulars are mentioned of the State of <pb n="3" facs="tcp:123920:2"/>affaires in England in the time of the late King, their Faithleſſe and bloody proceedings muſt more cleerly be manifeſt. And its proofe to all reaſonable men of a reſolved continuance in wicked undertakings, that they call the King <hi>a Tyrant,</hi> when not onely the mildneſſe of his nature, and Moderation of his privat and publique Actions, but the Peace and Proſperity of the People was ſo univerſally knowne to ſtrangers, and when in all that peeviſh diſcontent, or Traiterous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice could offer againſt him, there was no one Act in its nature and ſubſtance <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> but ſuch only, as were pretended might not be done by the King out of Parliament, and no one of theſe was done by the King, <hi>Regiâ manu, (with the Kingly power)</hi> but left to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters of Law, and Juſtice to decide in point of right, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute accordingly; but theſe men knowing how odious their Actions are, ſeeke a cover from reproachfull appellations upon the King, as if any could entertaine a prejudice by miſnaming perſons, or Actions, and if it were <hi>Tyranny</hi> for the King to do an Action out of Parliament, which he was adviſed by the Judges of law he juſtly might: how impudent are theſe men to reduce it? For where is the Parliament Authority for their vaſt levies of mony, Murder of the King, and the impoſing Lawes upon the people? Can a few perſons of the Lower Houſe, ſcarce the tenth part of the whole, by violence totally aboliſh both Houſes, and doe all Acts that belonged to the whole? And yet they perſwade the world they are beleeved in ſuch extravagant untruths. There need nothing be more ſaid how cauſeleſly the Rebells of <hi>England</hi> tooke Armes againſt the King. And if Rebells may pretend defence of their perſons againſt Soveraigne power, Malefactors will never want a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, when force is uſed to bring them to Juſtice. And is it <hi>one of the juſt and native liberties of the Engliſh nation,</hi> that the members of Parliament in the Lower Houſe being five hundred, forty of theſe may drive out the reſt, and doe what they pleaſe? this is the preſent caſe. But if we looke back, <hi>is it the liberty of England</hi> to be without a King, or to be ſubject to the power of one another, &amp; have no recourſe to their Prince for redreſſe! <hi>Is it the liberty of England,</hi> that a rabble of the City of <hi>London</hi> or an Army ſhall oppreſſe the Parliament and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound laws to oblige the whol Kingdom? <hi>Is it the liberty of England</hi> to exclude the King from making of laws, or governing the Militia? But they that are not aſhamed to act, yet ſeeme loath to ſpeak the things they doe. The ſeizing the Kings forts and navy, raiſing force againſt him and both Houſes of Parliament, puniſhing Judges for doing their <pb n="4" facs="tcp:123920:3"/>duty, and delivering their opinions in open Courts, againſt ſedition, licencing all lewd ſectaries and diſturbers of Government are
<hi>only aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting and deſire of ſetling juſt and native liberties.</hi> Thus they call their murders <hi>Juſtice,</hi> their robberies <hi>Reparation of Wrongs;</hi> And their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the King from one end of the Kingdome to the other, <hi>the defence of their lives and Eſtates.</hi> Its well ſeene, that thoſe men are the God of Gods anger upon the three Kingdoms, but they vainly flatter themſelvs to think that any beleeve it <hi>a bleſſing of God</hi> as they aſſume it, or <hi>that theſe wonders in ſo many ſignal battells, or that ſeries of providence was either in favour to them or their cauſe,</hi> and ſuch preſumptuous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences declare of what ſpirit men are, that they take up the language of
<hi>Senacharib,</hi> who came not without God againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the <hi>Turk,</hi> that attributes all his ſucceſſes againſt the
<hi>Chriſtians</hi> to the power of his <hi>falſe Prophet.</hi> And thoſe men that in their writings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, uſed the name of the whole Kingdom on their part, and the ſmall ſtrength of the King, now tells us of
<hi>an handfull of men that were faithfull to the cauſe,</hi> even ſo
<hi>faithfull,</hi> that they firſt brake al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance to their King, and then all fidelity to men. What they ſaid in this clauſe they ſay, <hi>was not intended to be mentioned,</hi> and indeed it no way concerned their preſent controverſie with the United Provinces, unleſſe they thought to ſcare all men by recounting their own Actions. But they proceed to ſay, <hi>neither is that indeavour to divide them in the memorable yeare of forty eight to be omitted.</hi> Surely the one might have been <hi>omitted</hi> as well as the other was <hi>not intended,</hi> for it hath nothing proper to their Declaration, unleſſe they meant to make their owne ſtory; And they very unſeaſonably mention <hi>the endeavour to divide them,</hi> when they were formerly divided, and the diviſion ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, and themſelves not onely endeavoured, but effected it, rej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cting both Scots and Presbyterian; Was not the new modell and change of the Generall their Act? And was not their diviſion further acted by purging the Houſe, and change of the Government?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor can they admit the great preparation against this Nation in the yeare,</hi> 1650. And what is all this to the United Provinces? And can they think any man believs, that preparations to aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the King, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſe them of their uſurpation, and reſtore the Nation to its juſt Rights, are preparations againſt the Nation? but this is the common ſtile of them Declarations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> (they ſay) <hi>neceſſitated their proceedings in Scotland, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſatisfaction for forepaſt wrongs, and denyed aſſurance of peace from <pb n="5" facs="tcp:123920:3"/>them, who had received the declared Enemy of the Commonwealth from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited provinces.</hi> Their guilt, and malice neceſſitated their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; for the Scots were obliged to receive their lawfull King, and will any accuſe Subject, for fidelity and obedience to their King, but ſuch as hate all piety and truth? but what were thoſe forepaſt wrongs? They had agreed with the Scots after the engagement of forty eight, which was the wrong pretended, and nothing can be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of peace to them, but a totall abdication of Loyalty, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the new Republican power of England. And it is their pretence of invaſion to have ſatisfaction upon mens eſtates, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by enſlaving their perſons. The Scots were unhappily m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſled in in their connection with the Engliſh in their Rebellion againſt the King, and found the reward of it from thoſe they aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted; And yet after they diſcerned the miſchievous conſequents of their undertaking upon their owne Nation, continued yet jealouſies of one another, and while they feared that, which might never happen, they ſuffered that, which they ſaw was unavoidably falling on them, the power of the Engliſh Rebells; And while ſome would act alone, and had feare of the event of a victory if they got it, betrayed all to the common Enemy. And what if they received the King from thoſe Provinces? Did he not come through the Dominions of the Kings of France &amp; Spaine? And what was the miſchievous contrivement, that was hatched there againſt England? Doubtleſſe if the contrivement were to bring in the King, it had been happy for England if it had taken effect But what is this to the United Provinces, if Strangers and Allies paſſe through their Countrey? But they ſay, <hi>their Enemies had much open and ſecret aſſiſtance by the Intereſt of the Prince of Orange; and others.</hi> And what law, or convention was there againſt it? had the United Provinces any League with England beſides what was made with the late King? and when their Ally dyes, muſt they quit all friendſhip to his heire?</p>
            <p>They ſay, <hi>it was a time, when the Prince, and his adherents were contriving as is moſt probable, to erect a Tyranny upon theſe Countryes, of which he miſſed but narrowly, eſpecially in his attempt upon Amſterdam, which things they ſay are better knowne there then heere, and are not the purpoſe of this Declaration.</hi> But it was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſet in to ſcatter jealouſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in their Provinces, and divide th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, &amp; endeavours againſt the malitious attempts of this common Enemy. The differences ariſing touching the attempt upon Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam were prudently compoſed and buryed by the States Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, <pb n="6" facs="tcp:123920:4"/>and no man will meaſure intentions by the malitious invectives of an Enemy, that contrives to effect that, which he ſaies another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rended. Tyrany is judged by the ſence, not by the fancy. But wiſemen will not by the apprehonſion of paſt or remote dangers make way for preſent. They ſay <hi>it is not pleaſant to remember the cruel and bloudy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Amboina, for which no ſatisfaction hath bin given though often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</hi> But never by them, when they ſent their Agents Ambaſſadors to treat, whereof they ſpeak afterwards; And if it were not pleaſant to them, they would rather have endeavoured ſatisfaction when they treated, then repetition when they were in hoſtility.</p>
            <p>Now they come to <hi>unkindneſſes</hi> received, <hi>that the Parliament ſent a Reſident to the States General, who refuſed to receive him.</hi> The reaſon is very apparent. The Parliament never had ſent any Reſident, neither was any ſuch Authority acknowledged by forreign States; And its a known Treaſon for the perſons in Parliament to doe ſuch an Act. Beſides the United Provinces were in league and amity with the King. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or ſuch, as called themſelves ſo, had not then renounced the Kingly Title, and ſtill allowed the Oaths of Allegeance, and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy to the King, and therefore their Reſident was ill ſent, and juſtly refuſed. But they think this amounts to an unkindneſs, <hi>ſince it proceeded from their affection to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, the eſtabliſhment of liberty &amp; advantage of traffique, and strength to both.</hi> Their affections are doubtles ſuch, as are uſuall between neer and potent Republiques, eſpecially where the advantages of traffique are the common aim of both, which not only creates emulations, but neceſſarily makes continued diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences till one be deſtroyed; and thence proceeded the Judgement of Qu.
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who concluded that the United Provinces muſt in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome deſire the ſtability of the Engliſh Monarchy, where by theſe rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures might be prevented, &amp; the Crown of England had greater aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe Provinces in the Government they were under, then if they had bin under a Prince, when new Alliances and engagements would continually change the affections and Councels of the Prince, but when theſe men ſent their Reſident, their affections were to their own intereſt, and they ſought to gain reputation by having a Reſident received, and to diminiſh the Kingly power abroad</p>
            <p>But <hi>the reaſon above al</hi> (they ſay) <hi>was the advancement of the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, which both profeſs, and which in humane probability would receive the greateſt growth by their friendſhip.</hi> The State of the United Provinces did not think, that England profeſſed not the true Proteſtant <pb n="7" facs="tcp:123920:4"/>Religion in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the Kings ſince, but the Religion thoſe new Governours profeſſe, no true Proteſtant will own for his, no one Church eſtabliſhed in any eſtate concurring with them; And as one chief Article in their Religion is upon their own private Authority <hi>to rob their neighbours and kill their Kings:</hi> ſo their doctrine and practice hath been a great ſcandall to the Proteſtant Religion, wherof they pretend to be. Their profeſſed opinions are deſtructive to humane ſociety, diſclaiming all ſubjection to Civil Governors, or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Synods, further then their private opinions concur with them, and maintaine not onely the reproaches of Rulers, but violence againſt them, if in their judgement they deſerve puniſhment to death, and this thoſe men would have to be the true Proteſtant Religion, and their affection to the Proteſtant Religion is ſeene in their cruelty to the Proteſtants of England.</p>
            <p>Next they obſerved <hi>in ſome of the Governors, and people of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries an affection to this cauſe, and expreſſed by them in their free contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the poore Proteſtants in Ireland.</hi> It is far from a probability, that any affected their cauſe, becauſe they contributed to the poore Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of Ireland. Themſelves well know, that very many contributed to the poore Proteſtants of Ireland, that hated the Rebellion, that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned it; &amp; if any man hated the Iriſh Rebellion, he muſt from the ſame grounds have deteſtation of a greater and more guilty, which followed in England; And the ſuffering Proteſtants in England are more in number, and for quality more eminent then thoſe in Ireland, and that of England hath had more barbarous effects, and is more incapable of excuſe, that of Ireland pretending difference of Nation and Religion, this of England pretending the ſame Religion, as they were of the ſame Nation; And its too well knowne both at home, &amp; abroad how many thoſe in England have robbed of their Eſtates, that not only contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the reliefe of the poor Proteſtants of Ireland, but hazarded their lives in that cauſe. And ſuch, as in the beginning of the troubles in England extended compaſſion to the poor Proteſtants of Ireland, diſcerned not the mercileſſe diſpoſition of thoſe men, that then go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned affaires in England, who never did one Act in order to their relief, but made uſe of their ſufferings to reproach the King; And by hypocriticall motions of other men to Charity ſought an opinion of Zeal to themſelves, and means to carry on the war in England againſt the King; And thoſe great ſummes, that were given to the reliefe of Ireland they converted to the maintenance of their own Rebellion in <pb n="8" facs="tcp:123920:5"/>England; and as many in theſe Provinces find the error they were in touching the integrity of the Reformers in England: So their Actions for the reliefe of the poor Proteſtents in Ireland will not prove, that they hated Rebellion leſſe in thoſe, that profeſſe the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion then the Popiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They joyned</hi> (they ſay) <hi>with their Reſident a worthy perſon Dr. Doriſlaus, who was barbarouſly, and openly murthered at the Hague the place of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the States General, of whoſe aſſaſſination the world will judge as of an Action moſt abhorred againſt all Rules of nationall intercourſe, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and how little was done to attach the murtherers muſt here be remembred.</hi> The quality of Dr. <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> is chiefly known by their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of him in forming their proceedings againſt their King to a ſtile of law and this negotiation they mention, which latter they might out of foreſight, knowing how odious the man was to the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, have forborne, and have ſent one not ſo deeply died in that bloud, for what care ſoever-ſtates take to reſtrain, and puniſh outward Actions, they cannot take away the univerſall indignation of a people againſt unnaturall and barbarous villanies. But <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> was killed in an houſe ſuddenly, which, though in the place of reſidence of the States Generall, thoſe complainers cannot pretend it in the power of the States Generall to have prevented, and they cannot intend <hi>the breach of all Rules of intercourſe, or humanity</hi> in that Act by the States, though they diſplay the fact with ſuch colours. They need not be told, that <hi>the Rules of intercourſe, and humanity</hi> allow no protection to common rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and enemies of humane ſociety; And thoſe men, that think the world ſo ready to make the Judgement they like, of this fact upon <hi>Doriſlaus,</hi> ſee not the Judgement themſelves given of their own aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and therein the Crime of <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> in the murder of the King: was not every man as much a Magiſtrate to execute <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> as they their King? And the Meſſengers of common deſtroyers cannot be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted publique Miniſters, but by whom they are acknowledged for ſuch. But if ſuch, as did the fact were unknown to the States General, how could they attach them, or if they were gone out of their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories though they were often called on? And why this muſt be here remembred as a nationall Injury is not viſible to any, but to ſhew the reſolution of theſe Governours to quarrel with the United Provinces, there having never bin a deniall of Juſtice, and legall proceedings?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The States</hi> (they ſay) <hi>ſent the Lords Borele, Renzwo, and Joachimi Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours in the time of the late troubles, pretending all good offices, which <pb n="9" facs="tcp:123920:5"/>proved a correſpondence with the Enemy, and a means of aſſiſting them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe, to whom they were ſent, this with reproaches by them caſt upon the Parliament was the work of theſe Embaſſadours.</hi> It was a friendly and worthy Action of the States of theſe Provinces to ſeek the compoſing of the troubles in England, and to interpoſe their Councel, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation in a work ſo becomming their Alliance; And it was no more then Juſtice to the King to correſpond with him, and theſe men of Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter muſt be remembred, that at this time they had not declared the King an Enemy, but they fought againſt evil Councellours, and they took up Arms for King, and Parliament, their party was not impudent enough then to avow the Titles they have ſince taken up. They well know theſe Embaſſadours were ſent to the King and though thye interceded with them, that called themſelves Parliament, it was in that manner as Embaſſadours addreſſe themſelves to treat with the Miniſters of Princes, to whom they are ſent; And theſe Embaſſadours then found what was doubtfull to many before, that the men then in hoſtility under the name of Parliament had abuſed the world with a pretence of neceſſity to take Armes for defence of Religion and lawes, ſeeking only power to themſelues, and an alteration of Religion and law, and that they had obſtinately refuſed all the gracious offers of the King, and his deſires of peace, and theſe Embaſſadours were bound in honour and fidelity to deal uprightly in their negotiation, &amp; to declare where the binderances of peace lay; And if the actions of the then pretended Parliament were reproachfull to themſelves, they cannot blame the Embaſſad ours for a faithfull report of them, &amp; this was very far from making them lyable by the practice of nations to puniſhment, or reproof; and it ſtood not with the affairs of the then Rebels in England to offer incivility to thoſe Embaſſadours, though they wanted not an inclination to it; &amp; thoſe Embaſſadours need not be carefull to anſwer for ſuch an Action, wherein they had cleere reaſon, and the warrant of their ſuperiours, to whom the complainers diſcovered the iniquity of their cauſe by ſo unjuſt an exception.</p>
            <p>They come now to the <hi>ſolemn Embaſſy</hi> they ſent the States, which (they ſay) <hi>was in a time when there was much leſs cauſe to apply to the States for any need the Parliament had of their aſſiſtance, for that England was wholly in their power, moſt of the Towns &amp; Cities in Ireland, the affairs of Scotland not unproſperous.</hi> But whoever took notice of the affairs then, knew very well they had neede of the forbearance of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces <pb n="10" facs="tcp:123920:6"/>from engaging againſt them which had they then acted, its probably they had prevented the progreſs of their victories, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them liable to their demerits; And what the men of Weſtminſter did in that Embaſſy was in order to their own affairs, not out of any priciples of affection to the Protyſtant Intereſt or common good. They endeavoured to draw the United Provinces into their own guilt by the league they propounded, ſo as theſe Provinces muſt have ſupported their uſurpation, and have drawn on them the infamy of Murdering the King and all the former Actions, whereby that uſurpation was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. Though Princes and States for the peace of their people ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times enter into leagues for comerce, with ſuch, who by wicked at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts have obteined the power of States, yet neither Religion nor civill Juſtice permit defence of unjuſt power; And when thoſe Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours diſcerned that the United Provinces could not be drawn into a ſcandalous league, then they deſerted the proſecution; And theſe tenders, which their Embaſſadours were impowered to make, that would have demonſtrated the affection of theſe in England to <hi>the good People</hi> of the United Provinces the ſame as to themſelves, ſufficiently demonſtrate their affection to the people of theſe Provinces to be only for themſelves; And the Priviledges they tendred to them were to divide them from their own State to a dependance on a forreign kindneſs, and was of the ſame ſtamp with this hypocriticall profeſſion to the good people of theſe Provinces, theſe good people being in their ſenſe ſuch, as would be ſeduced againſt their Country by their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, ſuch being their dealing with Scots pretending rather private enmity againſt ſome perſons, then Dominion over all, which was ſo apparently their Deſign, as it will be the ſhame of any, that ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after pretend ignorance of it. They ſay <hi>the Embaſſy was rendred of no effect becauſe the Embaſſadours were unheartily, and dilatorily dealt with.</hi> But the true reaſon was, that theſe Maſters had inſtructed their Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours to make no agreement without the abſolute ſubmiſſion of theſe Provinces to them. If their Embaſſadours were unſafe in their perſons, it was not by any neglect of the States of the United Provinces, who placed a ſufficient guard about them, &amp; puniſhed ſuch as offered indignities to them, and if their Embaſſadours concealed it, they dealt unfaithfully with their ſuperiours, and unjuſtly with them they were ſent to: And when it appeared the States of the United Provinces would not partake in the guilt of that blood, and uſurpation with theſe Maſters in England, the Embaſſadours were recalled home.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:123920:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That the States Generall ſent not an Embaſſy till after the defeat at Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> is true, and the willingneſs and affectection with which it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, doth teſtifie for the Engliſh part, they ſtood <hi>fixed to their former Principles,</hi> which were to ſerve themſelves of the power, and Intereſt of the vinced Provinces; for to prepare for the Embaſſadours entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they had made an Act as they call it, <hi>that no commodities ſhould be brought into England by any forraign veſſels, but ſuch as were of the growth of that Country, to which ſuch veſſell belonged,</hi> which tooke away that traffique, and intercourſe, which was in all ages continued betweene the nations, and had no other ſcope but to interrupt the trade of theſe Provinces: And as this Act teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fies what principles they went in to deſtroy the trade, and navall ſtrength of the United Provinces, ſo they being the ſame they had in their former proceedings, and ſending their Embaſſy, they vainly pretend affection to Religion, Liberty, or amity with this Country, while they expreſſe a malicious Deſign to enſlave, or deſtroy it from their firſt Treaty with them.</p>
            <p>They finde fault <hi>that in the Treaty the States Ambaſſadours evaded poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive demands in things not of hardeſt reſolution with allegations of want of power, though their Commiſſion ſhewed no ſuch reſtraint.</hi> The age of theſe mens rule in England may be read in theſe frivolous objections. Though Embaſſadors have an abſolut commiſſion, are they not tyed to inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? And are there not particular laws, &amp; cuſtomes in States, that limit Embaſſadours, and yet not expreſſed in their Commiſſion? But whence comes the Allegation of want of power to be an evaſion? And <hi>becauſe the Provincial States muſt be aſſembled before anſwers could be had, it gave ſmall grounds of any real intendment of a firm peace, and amity.</hi> It was a firm ground of averſion to peace in thoſe of England, that they were poſitive in ſuch demands, as muſt enforce the meeting of the Provinciall States to give a reſolution. Upon the comming of the Embaſſadours of the States General into England, its well knowne what licence was taken by mean people to abuſe them: And to let them know what they muſt truſt to, a Treatiſe is compoſed, &amp; publiſhed of the buſineſs of
<hi>Amboina,</hi> which had reſted for ſo many years, and till then unmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by thoſe affectionate ſeekers of amity with the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. Herein they provoke the people to aſſume an hatred of theſe Provinces, &amp; to ſeek revenge for an Act ſo long paſſed. If they had intended amity, or thought a ſtrict Alliance with theſe Provinces ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, why would they renew the memory of old differences, or fix an averſion in the people to thoſe, with whom they treated for peace?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123920:7"/>This might have bin a proper work after a treaty broken, but to make ſuch a narration the Prologue to a Treaty, is a ſure ground, that no peace was intended, but ſuch, as force and terrour could extort; And that ſuch propſitions muſt be granted to obtein it as a conquered people only muſt ſubmit to, and they muſt needs give way to the exerciſe of the peoples licence, and hatred that uſed the means to work it in them. And this deſigne of the Rulers being known it was ſoon proſecuted, their ordinary Agents, the Preachers and compoſers of Gazetts, and Almanacks publiſhed it to the world, and from thence came theſe predictions of their South ſayers
<hi>of the destruction of Holland;</hi> And theſe diſcuourſes of their Politiques of ſubjecting ſuch powers, as might be prejudiciall to the new Babell they had raiſed in England, and therefore the United Provinces being able to do them harm, they muſt have theſe Countries in ſuch a Chaine, as may draw them that way onely where thoſe new Rulers ſhall move, and like formes of Govenment are no more to them then the brotherhood of
<hi>Scotland.</hi> It cannot be preſumed, that the ſervants ſpeak other than their Maſters ſenſe; And if it had bin contrary, it would have appeared in their reſtraint, or puniſhment; And theſe Rulers vainely offer an exception of dilatorineſſe on the part of the United Provinces when there were ſo many of their ſhips continually taken, and made prize during the Teraty, and the danger of thoſe Provinces muſt be increaſed by delay, the ſeaſons of their Trade, and return of their ſhips being known, and unſafe while the Treaty was unconluded.</p>
            <p>And its will known the preparation of Shipe in England proceded thoſe of Holland; And though they ſpeak <hi>of preparations upon the notice the Embaſſadours of the States General gave them of ſetting out a hundred, and fifty ſail of ſhips beſides the men of war abroad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> all men know the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in England, and affronts received neceſſarily occaſioned that care in the States Generall. But thoſe of England were offended that the States Generall ſhould defend their Merchants, which they meant to make prize of; And beſides the exerciſe of repriſals on the ſhips of the United Provinces, the grounds, on which their Commiſſions of Repriſall were granted, ſhewed it no other then an open hoſtility, as that, which was to repair one, that was intercepted by the States ſhips carrying ſupplies out of England into Flanders before the peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe Countries, and the King of Spain, and others of leſſe colour. It is eaſily believed, they altered not their reſolutions upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the States prepations; But that they made Juſtice, honour, and mutuall good the Rule to ſteere their Actions by, is incredible to any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123920:7"/>that knew their former, or preſent Actions: For is it Juſtice to grant, letters of Repriſall upon a particular caſe, unleſſe Juſtice be firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for the fact and denyed? And can it ſtand with honour, Juſtice, and mutual good to require unequal conditions, &amp; an abſolute ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for peace? And the happy cloſe of the Treaty, which theſe: Rulers were willing to come to, appears no other but to have the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces under their command: For the Accidents touching Captaine <hi>Young,</hi> and Admirall <hi>Tromp</hi> by the narrative, which the Uſurpers of England, have publiſhed, the world will judge, that they ſought an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion againſt the United Provinces, and to renounce all amity with them; And their aggravation adds not weight of Argument for what they offer, for <hi>if the middeſt of a Treaty</hi> be conſiderable, why did thoſe men of peace continue Repriſalls <hi>in the middeſt of the ſame Treaty?</hi> But it is ridiculous to affirme, <hi>that the Dutch Admiral ſought out their Shipps in their own ſeas,</hi> when the trade way of thoſe ſeas is ſuch, as a meeting of ſhipps is not eaſily avoided; Beſides the peaceable demeanour of the Admirall <hi>Tromp,</hi> till he received the ſhots from <hi>Blake.</hi> But this is their accuſtomed language, their Declarations againſt the King being fraught with ſuch ſtuffe of making a bloudy war upon the Parliament rejecting their humble deſires, and of dangerous plots againſt the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Kingdom. But the truth of this fact is fully known, and the vanity of theſe declarers aggravation. And it bears full proof in it ſelf, that the Fleet under the command of Tromp <hi>came</hi> not <hi>purpoſely into the Roade of England</hi> unto their Fleet, and by all the atteſtations produced, he ſhewed no inclination to hoſtillity; And thoſe men that make al cleer on their part, like not a way of <hi>equall examination becauſe long &amp; intricate, but would kave a ſubmiſſion to their own allegations, and a ſatisfaction for the wroags they pretended;</hi> And they believe, that men underſtand not, that they could make their demands for ſatisfaction ſuch, as would take up longer debate, then that examination, and in the mean time proceed with all hoſtillity, which they would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear till that demand were ſatisfied; And when could the States Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors aſſure themſelves that they would determine their demands?</p>
            <p>The reaſon they give for their Counſel is <hi>that time being gained an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſtrength might therwith be provided by the Dutch</hi> &amp; from hence the reſolved hoſtility of the Rulers is evident, &amp; that they had provided to take the Dutch unprepared, &amp; were offended that they had a fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et. It cannot be conceived that theſe Engl. Maſters having propounded to have ſatisfaction for wrongs upon their own Allegations only without reſpect to what was offred to the contrary, <hi>that they would treat with ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123920:8"/>moderation, as ſuch, as treated with them ſhould Judge reaſonable,</hi> but would be ſole Judges of the ſatisfaction, as they made themſelves of the cauſe, for which they demanded it; and if they would not heare all proofes in the one caſe, they were not likely to admit any reaſon in the other; And they might very well offer a ceſſation of hoſtility upon their owne termes. They projected <hi>their ſatisfaction for their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations becauſe the Dutch had prepared a fleete,</hi> and yet never excepted to it when notice was given them, and they enlarge this ſatisfaction to loſſes of all kinde, in the dammage of the ſhipps, loſſe of men, and the poverty of perſons thereby, and under thoſe heads who could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture the quantity of the ſatisfaction, they would thinke a fit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, and in the meane time no ceſſation, and all Accidents ſucceeding muſt be caſt into the account, which might be prolonged at the pleaſure of thoſe, that got by the delay; And yet thoſe confident men thinke it ſtrange, <hi>that the</hi> Lord Embaſſadour <hi>Paw did not purſue his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſire of ceſſation,</hi> when by their anſwer they ſhewed their reſolution to keep it in their own power to ſet the time to it, and was no more then if they had anſwered, it ſhould be at their pleaſure, and yet they are not aſhamed to ſay, <hi>it was in his own power to accompliſh it.</hi> Can any man think it was in his power to accompliſh what they would demand? And is it not a deſperate compliance for any State to continue treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, while hoſtillity is avowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and terms only propounded of abſolute ſubmiſſion to avoid it? Thus the Embaſſadours were forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to preſerve the honour, and ſafety of themſelves, and their Country. It ſeems thoſe Declarers think they merited <hi>by giving reſpect and accommodation to the Ambaſſadours:</hi> And conſidering their other actions, and diſpoſition, worſe might have been expected, but they found it not for their preſent advantage, nor doth the mention of their yeilding to <hi>reſpect and accommodation</hi> tend to their honour, as if it were queſtionable whither they ſhould have performed it, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their abode they neither expected, nor found better uſage then the Miniſters of theſe Rulers found from the States of the United Provinces; and they had not merited that averſion of the people, which was univeſally expreſſed to the Miniſters of thoſe Rulers.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Narrative</hi> by them publiſhed, they hold a ſufficient juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Acts of hoſtillity, and deteining ſhipps brought into their Ports without any precedent Declaration, or notice to the Embaſſadours then in Treaty. The Narrative is of one ſide onely giving no anſwer to contrary atteſtations; and though it be evident to all reaſonable <pb n="15" facs="tcp:123920:8"/>men, that the fact was accident all and undeſignet by Tromp, yet this Narrative is all the reaſon they will give for a preſent hoſtility, neither could any proſecution be looked for before the caſe were fully exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, where friendſhip was ſo confidenly profeſſed. Neither had their forbearance been <hi>laying downe of themſelves at the feete of any.</hi> But the ſpeedy feirce purſuit ſhewes not a ſudden paſſion, but a long premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Counſell for the oppreſſion of the United Provinces, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their trade, and ſtrength by ſea, and yet ſo ſhameleſſe are they to call this proceeding <hi>their owne defence, and if they had done contrary, it had been againſt the truſt repoſed in them,</hi> few men thinke the Actions of theſe Declarers agreeable to any rules, whereby nations or ſingle perſons are governed, and breach of truſt is of no regard with them, for there was not any truſt repoſed in them by King, or people, but what they have moſt perfidiouſly broken; that truſt, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in them as ſubjects, whereto they were bound by Religion, Law, and nature, they have falſified to their King and Countrey. They were called by the Kings writ, and by law incapable of any place in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till they had taken the oaths of Allegeance, and Supremacy. They were truſted to petition the King, and offer their Councell, they deſtroy the King inſteede of petitioning, make laws, and change the Government in deſpight of the truſt they pretend to regard. If we examine their Doctrines, they maintai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> themſelves not bound to oaths longer then they think fit. If we look upon their proceedings, they have acted accordingly, breaking all oaths, and promiſes, the truſt, whereon depends humane ſociety, aſſerting falſhood and abju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring truths. There are numerous Teſtimonies of all theſe in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and Treaties with the King,
<hi>that they would make him a glorious King; that it never entred into their thought to depoſe him; that if they ſhould charge the King with any evill Action, it were contrary to the law, and the Teſtimony of their owne Conſcience; That providing for the prosperity of his Majeſty who proteſt in the preſence of all ſeeing Deity to be the end of all our Counſells; That they have nothing in their thoughts more precious next to the honour and immediate ſervice of God, then their juſt and faithfull performance of their duty to his Majeſty.</hi> This being compared with their actions who can repoſe truſt in them; Beſides, they are not truſted by the Kingdom, and thoſe few of them that were depuzed by particular places were not truſted to rule, but they now tiranize, and trample on ſuch, as at firſt truſted them; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring their Actions towards the united Provinces, and their words <pb n="16" facs="tcp:123920:9"/>we may Judge they are not changed in their principles, for they ſay by <hi>thoſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings it will be more then evident with what affection, and conſtancy the Parliament have laboured for the friend ſh of he United Provinces, how carefully they avoided all differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and occaſions of a warre between the nations, though all ſuch overtures of amity, and neereſt alliance having been rejected.</hi> In the beginning of the wicked Rebellion in England, not only the common people at home, but ſtrangers were much miſtaken of the condition and intention of thoſe, that made themſelves a party againſt the King, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y perſwading themſelves, that the prevalent party in Parliament had the ſame ſincerity in their purpoſes, which they profeſſed in their ſpeeches, and papers. But ſuch, as were then deceived, ſee the diſcovery of their e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rour, and that thoſe pretences of Religion, Law, and Loyalty were only ſnares, whereby they were ſeduced to their owne ruine: And though the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt loſſe lighted on the King, and his Loyall ſubjects, the whole Kingdome hath ſelt the ſcourge of that credulity: And while ſome were miſled, and others reſted ſecure, as unconcerned, not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the conſequents of popular conteſts with Soveraignty, the whole are brought under the Tyrannicall power of a few contemptible perſons: And ſuch, as with dry eyes beheld the ſufferings of the King and his party, finde the ſame fince at their owne doores: And ſuch, as acted under the name of Parliament againſt the King are now oppreſſed under the ſame pretence, which themſelves uſed, they perſwading men they were the Parliament, though the King and the greateſt part of the Lords, and a great number of the Commons were forced away, and the remaining party overawed by the City Tumults and Army, now groane under this new power, that call themſelves a Parliament, though the King be murdered, the Lords houſe ſhut up, the greateſt part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons impriſoned, and expelled. And onely a few perſons ſit, as a Lower Houſe without any colour of Law. The neglect of oppoſition to growing evills is often too late repented, and ſuch, as doubted not what hath hapned in England, may now ſee, that wickedneſſe puts no bounds to it ſelfe. It muſt be reſiſtance, from without, not the inward inclination that muſt reſtraine it; And where men have ſucceſſe, and an opinion of ſtrength, they reſt not at a ſtay eſpecially new gained powers, and the Example of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe perſons is no leſſe dangerous, then their power. Princes and States are cheifely concerned in ſuppreſſing ſuch pernicious Monſters, whoſe opinions and Deſignes are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Rulers, and draw with them the miſery of the people, who muſt fall into confuſion and ſlavery. If their deſigne take upon the United Provinces, it may be eaſily conjectured what their attempts will be next. And affection to an oppreſſed King, and Ally, amity to the Engliſh nation, ſecurity to Religion and commerce, call for a conjunction of the hearts and hands of all Chriſtian Kings and States againſt thoſe common Enemyes of mankind.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
